IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Caress, Mark April 22, 1994, 91-256; 18 pages; 1 audiocassette, 42 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Mark Caress received his BA from Indiana University in 1948 and stayed involved with the university for many years thereafter earning an advanced degree, as a teacher, and as president of the Indiana University Alumni Association. He went on to a career in baking, serving as a bank president for 20 years. Caress discusses the differences between undergraduate and graduate life, Indiana University presidents, the campus atmosphere after World War II, and what he sees in the future for Indiana University.
  Hoosiers for Higher Education; University Apartments
  assistant superintendent; assistant to the director of the division of research and field services; bank president; Indiana Association of Public School Superintendents president; Indiana Bankers' Association president; Indiana University Alumni Association president; teacher; United States Civil Service Commission federal investigator
  Akins, Claude; Church, Harold; Franzen, Carl; Rinnick, Red; Ryan, John W.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  Bedford, Indiana; Crawfordsville, Indiana; Martinsville, Indiana
  1944 GI Bill; army barracks; drugs; Great Depression; Indiana University alumni; testing; traffic; university funding; World War II
- Carmichael, William P. June 16, 1994, 91-275; 9 pages; 1 audiocassette, 18 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  William Carmichael attended Indiana University from 1961 to 1965. After receiving his BA, he went on to law school and ended up working for an accounting firm doing tax work. Carmichael discusses what the university's campus was like in the nineteen sixties and some of the student activism on campus. He also talks about the connections he's had to Indiana University since graduation, including the membership on the board of several School of Business organizations and his involvement with the Indiana University Foundation.
  Fair Play for Cuba Committee; Indiana University Foundation; International Business Forum
  attorney; School of Business Alumni Association Board member
  Ehrlich, Thomas
  Valparaiso, Indiana
  accounting; university funding; Vietnam War
- Carmony, DonaldJuly 12, 1994, 91-280; 34 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 119 minutes; index; obituary from Indianpolis Star, obituary from Indiana Daily Student; Freedman, Jean
  Donald Carmony, born January 18, 1910, in Shelby County, Indiana and died February 14, 2005. He discusses his experience growing up in Indiana and his education background. He goes into detail about his experiences as a professor at Fort Wayne, South Bend, and Bloomington campuses. Further, he discusses his time as Academic Dean for all Indiana University extension centers. Lastly, he discusses his personal teaching philosophies.
  University of Indianapolis
  Fort Wayne, Indiana; Indianapolis, Indiana; Shelby County, Indiana; South Bend, Indiana
  farmer; teacher; professor
  Anderssohn, John; Briscoe, Herman; Cavanugh, Dean; Ehrlich, Thomas; Esarey, Logan; Kohlmeier, Alfred; Ryan, John; Stahr, Elvis; Sutton, Joe; Wells, Herman; Wilkie, Wendell
  Great Depression; history; teaching experiences
- Carter, Byrum E., Jr. May 10, 1991, 91-060; 26 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 81 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on March 3, 1922, Byrum E. Carter worked at Indiana University from 1947 until 1987 in the capacity of political science professor, assistant dean of faculties, dean of the college, and chancellor of the Bloomington campus. Carter discusses the impact of veterans in the student population after World War II, the growth of the university and its graduate programs, and campus politics. In addition, he speaks of campus controversy as exemplified by the 1969 boycott and the Ballantine Lock-In. Carter recalls Indiana University under the administrations of Herman B Wells, Elvis J. Stahr, and John Ryan.
  faculty council
  political science professor
  Brenneman, Bill; Gucker, Frank G.; Parker, Keith; Ryan, John W.; Sonneborn, Tracy; Stahr, Elvis J.; Weimar, Arthur M.; Wells, Herman B; Work, Jim
  1969 Indiana University boycott; Ballantine Lock-In; campus politics; graduate programs; minority faculty; student unrest; university growth; Vietnam War; World War II veterans
- Clapacs, J. Terry November 22, 1993, 91-221; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 26, 1943, J. Terry Clapacs is an Indiana University alumnus from the class of 1965 and a 1968 graduate of the School of Business. In this interview, he discusses his years as a student and his career as an administrator at Indiana University. Until 1976, Clapacs was the contract manager, then he became the director of university physical facilities, then vice president of facilities, and finally, the vice president for administration. He discusses memories of major events during his years as a student including the assassinations of John F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King, Jr. and the Vietnam War.
  university administrator
  Kennedy, John Fitzgerald; King, Martin Luther, Jr.; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.
  Cuban Missile Crisis; John F. Kennedy assassination; Martin Luther King, Jr. assassination; Vietnam War
- Clarke, Brian Goodwin April 13, 1994, 91-246; 10 pages; 1 tape, 22 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on November 9, 1956, Brian Goodwin Clarke is an Indiana University alumnus from the early nineteen eighties and a former student body president. In this interview, he recalls his years as a student at Indiana University in the mid nineteen seventies; during this time he was a member of the Phi Kappa Psi fraternity and has many positive memories of his experiences with Greek life. In addition, Clarke comments on his efforts and accomplishments as student body president.
  Phi Kappa Psi
  Danzig, Steve; Gambill, Chris
  fraternities
- Clüver, Claus February 16, 1996; April 1, 1996, 96-004; 61 pages; 4 tapes; index; curriculum vitae; Kraemer, Peter
  Born on October 25, 1932, Claus Clüver came to Indiana University from Hamburg, Germany from 1957 through 1959, and permanently in 1964, to help found the Department of Comparative Literature. Clüver served in several positions including associate instructor, lecturer, associate professor, and full professor of comparative literature. In addition, he helped to begin overseas studies programs through Indiana University in Hamburg, Germany and in São Paulo, Brazil. In this interview, Clüver discusses the development and history of comparative literature and his involvement in the creation of the Interarts Studies Program at Indiana University. He speaks of international students at the university, racism, campus changes, changes in enrollment, and some of the effects of the energy crisis on the university. Finally, some of the names prominent in Clüver's interview and in the field of comparative literature are Horst Frenz, Ulrich Weisstein, Mary Ellen Solt, and Clifford Flannigan.
  Indiana University Department of Comparative Literature
  comparative literature professor
  Chaitin, Gil; Flannigan, Clifford; Frenz, Horst; Mitchell, Briand; Solt, Mary Ellen; Weisstein, Ulrich
  Hamburg, Germany; São Paulo, Brazil
  campus changes; energy crisis; enrollment; interarts studies; international students; racism; study abroad programs
- Cohen, H. Daniel December 2, 1993, 91-226; 16 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 41 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Daniel Cohen, born in 1937, speaks from his perspective as the chancellor of Indiana University at South Bend about the regional campus system. He emphasizes South Bend's growth as a campus center and its distinctiveness; for example, the majority of Indiana University at South Bend's student body consists of nontraditional students. This contributes to the uniqueness of the education and student services that Indiana University at South Bend offers. In addition, Cohen speaks of the effects of tuition increases on this regional campus.
  Indiana University South Bend
  university chancellor
  South Bend, Indiana
  nontraditional students; tuition increases
- Collins, Dorothy May 16, 1994, 91-254; 36 pages; 2 tapes, 100 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on October 11, 1912, Dorothy Collins came to Indiana University in 1939 to pursue doctoral studies. Instead, she married Ralph Collins and worked in a variety of capacities at the university, including work in what became the Collins Living-Learning Center with her husband, the Kinsey Institute, and for several Indiana University presidents. She worked especially closely with Elvis J. Stahr and Herman B Wells, specifically in the capacity of ghost-writing speeches. In this interview, Mrs. Collins recalls many influences on the university such as the McCarthy era, university growth, the issues pertaining to minority and female students, and the administration.
  Indiana University Collins Living-Learning Center; Indiana University Department of English; Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction
  Bryan, Charlotte Lowe; Collins, Ralph; Ehrlich, Thomas; Hershey, Amos S.; Kabisch, Ernest Bernard; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Morrison, Sarah Parke; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Visher, Stephen Sargent; Wells, Herman B
  African-Americans; Ballantine Lock-In; Indiana University administration; McCarthyism; minority students; university growth; women's movement; World War II
- Crooks, Edwin W. February 28, 1992, 91-084; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 51 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on July 29, 1919, Edwin W. Crooks received his business doctorate from Indiana University in 1959. Less than an decade later, he returned to Indiana University and began what would become a twenty-year long career as the director, dean, and then chancellor Indiana University Southeast. In this interview, Crooks discusses the growth of the regional campus system, especially that of Indiana University Southeast. Included is a comparison of the Bloomington campus and the Indiana University Southeast campus. Crooks mentions significant personalities with regard to Indiana University Southeast including George Pinnell and Sam Braden.
  Indiana University Southeast
  Braden, Sam; Pinnell, George; Stahr, Elvis J.
  New Albany, Indiana
  Indiana University Southeast campus; Indiana University Southeast growth; nontraditional students
- Cross, Patrick September 23, 1993, 91-200; 13 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 38 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Patrick Cross received his BA from Indiana University in 1987 and returned to campus in the early nineteen nineties to obtain his JD. He was president of the student body from 1986 to 1987. Cross talks about campus activism in the nineteen eighties, especially issues involving South Africa. He also discusses his tenure as student body president and what it was like to serve on the search committee for Indiana University's new president. He finishes up by talking about his career after graduation and his experiences attending law school at Indiana University.
  attorney; Republican caucus legislative coordinator; student body president; wrestler
  Ehrlich, Thomas; McCaig, Dick
  South Africa
  campus activism; campus infrastructure; diversity; governor's fellowship; Indiana University regional campuses; law school; shanty town; search committee; student government; university mission statement
- Daly, Walter Joseph June 27, 1994, 91-278; 15 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 43 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Walter Joseph Daly was born in Michigan City, Indiana, in 1930. His family moved to Muncie, Indiana, when he was 3. Daly attended Indiana University starting in 1947 and majored in zoology as a pre-medical school subject. He attended Indiana University School of Medicine, did a residency, served in the army, and did research before joining the Indiana University School of Medicine faculty. In 1970, he became chair of the department of internal medicine and dean of the school in 1983. He reflects on the mission of Indiana University and its medical school, the university's presidents, the cost of tuition and the cost of health care.
  Indiana University School of Medicine
  medical professor; School of Medicine dean
  Bryan, William Lowe; Harmon, Paul; Ritchey, James O.; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  health care; HIV/AIDS; medical practice; medical school; student debt; zoology
- Danielson, Donald C. August 29, 1991; October 4, 1991, 91-075; 16 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 76 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on December 3, 1919, Donald C. Danielson received his undergraduate degree from Indiana University in 1942. After service in the United States navy and a long and successful career as a businessman, and continuing involvement in alumni affairs, he became a member of the Indiana University board of trustees. Danielson was a trustee from 1959 until 1980 and was chair of the board of trustees for eleven of those years. Danielson recalls memories of his days as a student including anecdotes illustrating the empathy and spirit of Herman B Wells. In addition, Danielson discusses how the administrations of Indiana University presidents have differed. He also speaks of the difficult transition from president Joseph Sutton to president John Ryan.
  Sigma Chi
  Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Wells, Herman B
  Indiana University regional campuses; university growth
- Day, Harry May 18, 1994, 91-258; 26 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 82 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Harry Day came to Indiana University in 1940 as a chemistry professor and remained at Bloomington for the rest of his career. Day tells the story of the discovery of Crest toothpaste. He also talks about the changes that have taken place at the University since the nineteen forties, the development of the chemistry department, the effects of national events, like the Civil Rights Movement, on Indiana University, and the different Indiana University presidents and their legacies.
  American Chemical Society; Central High School; Cornell University; Indiana Daily Student; Indiana University Department of Chemistry; Indiana University School of Dentistry; Indiana University School of Medicine; Johns Hopkins University; National Science Foundation; Proctor and Gamble
  chemistry professor
  Briscoe, Herman T. "Kay"; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Kinsey, Clara M.; Lyons, Robert; Mathers, Frank Curry; McCollum, E.V.; Muhler, Joseph; Payne, Fernandus; Shriner, Ralph; Wells, Herman B
  Iowa
  1918 Influenza Epidemic; accreditation; biochemistry; chemistry; Civil Rights Movement; Crest toothpaste; dentists; discrimination; enamel; farming; fluoride; Indiana University presidents; segregation; Sputnik; World War II
- Doninger, Clarence H. May 5, 1992, 91-105; 16 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 46 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Clarence Doninger, born in 1935, recalls his lifelong association with Indiana University: his undergraduate degree in 1957 and law degree in 1960, involvement in the Men's Club, Varsity Club, athletic committee, and Alumni Association, and finally his tenure as athletic director, starting in 1991. He reflects on his own days as a student, changes in university in the last half of the twentieth century, and the complexities of intercollegiate sports under the NCAA.
  Indiana University Alumni Association; Indiana University Athletic Committee; Indiana University Men's Club; National Collegiate Athletic Association
  athletic director; attorney
  college sports; Indiana University alumni affairs; Indiana University alumni club; student athletes; student life; university growth; university physical plant; varsity club
- Dunn, Oscar October 7, 1993, 91-205; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 35 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on June 21, 1914, Oscar Dunn was a student at Indiana University from 1932 until he graduated in 1936, after which he began a long and successful career with General Electric. Dunn relates some anecdotes of his days as a student and some experiences with Herman B Wells, whom he credits with great wisdom and spirit. In addition, Dunn discusses Indiana University's tremendous growth in the nineteen seventies while remembering the harder days of the Great Depression. He also speaks of the important actions and successes of the Indiana University Foundation.
  Indiana University Foundation
  Cookson, Thomas A.; Wells, Herman B
  Great Depression; Indiana University administration; university growth
- Dutton, Clarence Benjamin "Ben" June 20, 1994, 91-269; 21 pages; 2 tapes, 75 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Clarence Benjamin "Ben" Dutton, born on May 31, 1917, earned his undergraduate degree in business administration from Indiana University in 1938 and his law degree from the Indiana University School of Law in 1940. After service in the United States Navy, Dutton returned to Bloomington to teach in the Indiana University School of Law for a few years, after which he set up his own law practice in Indianapolis. He recalls his years as a student, detailing some effects of the Great Depression and issues such as housing and laundering clothes. In addition, he discusses changes on the Indiana University campus, the era of McCarthyism, World War II, and his relations with Herman B Wells. Dutton also speaks of the efforts of the Indiana University alumni association.
  Indiana University Alumni Association
  law professor
  Bryan, William Lowe; Cathcart, Jimmy; Edwards, Edward D.; Harper, Fowler V.; Nelson, Alice; Wells, Herman B
  campus development; Great Depression; McCarthyism; student housing; student life; university growth; World War II
- Dye, James July 28, 1992, 91-133; 21 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 72 minutes, index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  James Dye attended Indiana University from 1949 to 1953. After graduation he served as a real estate officer in Korea and went to work in real estate and construction. His university connection continued and he was appointed to the board of trustees. He discusses the search for President Ehrlich, his impressions of past and present presidents, the relationship between research and teaching, and how Indiana University has changed over time.
  Architectural Committee; Army ROTC; Sigma Chi; Union Board
  architect; board of trustees member; logger; real estate agent
  Clapacs, Terry; Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  1944 GI Bill; football; Korean War; real estate; retirement plan; teaching vs. research debate
- Earnhart, Don B. May 7, 1992, 91-103; 12 pages; 1 7/8 ips, 38 minutes, index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Don B. Earnhart attended Indiana University as an undergraduate, graduating in 1949. He then went to work as an accountant for the Inland Container Corporation, owned by the Krannert family. The Krannerts planned to give money to Indiana University after their deaths and Mr. Earnhart became the administrative trustee of the Krannert Charitable Trust, which gave millions of dollars to the university. Earnhart also remained directly involved in the university himself, serving as director and treasurer of the Indiana University Foundation. In addition to this, he discusses university funding and the changes that have taken place on campus.
  Board of Aeons; Inland Container Corporation; Krannert Charitable Trust
  Krannert
  accountant; administrative trustee; Indiana University Foundation director; student supreme court chief justice
  accounting; philanthropy; student body; university funding; World War II
- Edmondson, Frank K. October 30, 1996, 96-027; 72 pages; 3 tapes; index; journal; Kraemer, Peter
  Frank K. Edmondson earned his undergraduate degree in 1933 and his masters degree in 1934 from Indiana University. After earning his Ph.D. in astronomy from Harvard, he joined the Indiana University Department of Astronomy in 1937, and became chairman of the department in 1944, a position he held until 1978. He speaks of his academic roots at Seymour High School, his experiences at Indiana University, and his use and/or association with the Lowell, Harvard, Goethe Link, and Kirkwood observatories. In addition, Edmondson speaks of many of the leading figures in the field of astronomy, including Henry Norris Russell and Wilber Cogshall, and he discusses the development and changes undergone by the Indiana University Department of Astronomy. He recalls the effects of Sputnik on this field and his involvement with associations such as the National Science Foundation, or NSF, and the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, or AURA. Finally, he recalls his experiences and interactions with many people at Indiana University including Herman B Wells and Alfred Kinsey.
  Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Incorporated; Goethe Link Observatory; Harvard Observatory; Indiana University Department of Astronomy; Indiana University Kirkwood Observatory; Lawrence Fellowship; Lowell Observatory; National Science Foundation; Seymour High School
  Russell
  astronomer; astronomy professor
  Aller, Lawrence; Cogshall, Wilbur A.; Cuffey, Jim; Kinsey, Alfred C.; Russell, Henry Norris; Shapley, Harlow; Townsend, Prescott; Wells, Agnes E.; Wells, Herman B; Williams, Kenneth P.
  campus development; faculty meetings; Sputnik
- Ehrlich, Thomas January 25, 1994, 91-233; 17 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 57 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Thomas Ehrlich was born in Massachusetts and attended Harvard Law School. Despite his legal background, he held a variety of jobs including assistant to the undersecretary of the state, president of the Legal Services Corporation, and head of the Foreign Aid program. He became president of Indiana University in 1987. Ehrlich discusses his presidential agenda, preference for a "responsibility-centered" management style, Indiana University's Indiana University regional campuses, the financial situation at the university, and the conflicts over teaching versus research.
  Brookings Institute; Harvard University; Legal Services Corporation; Stanford University
  assistant to the under-secretary of the state; attorney; college president; foreign aid program director; law clerk; law professor; law school dean; Legal Services Corporation president
  Ball, George A.; Chayes, Abram; Hand, Learned; Wells, Herman B
  Massachusetts
  Indiana University regional campuses; international law; research; university budget; university funding
- Eichhorn, FriedrichNovember 8, 1993, 91-216; 22pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 39 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Friedrich Eichhorn, born October 16, 1930 in Gary, Indiana, was a student at Indiana University Northwest and Indiana University Bloomington. Upon graduation from law school, he returned to Gary to work in a law firm and eventually became a senior partner. He discusses his time at both Indiana University Northwest and Indiana University Bloomington as well as his time serving on the Board of Trustees.
  Board of Trustees; Indiana University Northwest
  Gary, Indiana
  lawyer
  Korean War; student experiences; student involvement; students
- Eisenberg, Paul January 30, 1997; February 6, 1997, 96-032; Not transcribed; 3 tapes, 155 minutes; Kraemer, Peter
  Paul Eisenberg joined the Indiana University faculty in 1966 as a member of the Philosophy Department, where he served until 1997. In this interview, he discusses the developments of and his experiences with the Philosophy Department, especially emphasizing his years as department chair. Eisenberg also speaks of his early life and his education, in addition to his teaching views and practices. Finally, he discusses the faculty council.
  faculty council; Indiana University Department of Philosophy
  teaching